恐龙曾统治地球...
Dinosaurs ruled the planet
(大卫爱登堡主持)
...超过一亿五千万年
for over 150 million years.
几乎在地球的每个角落 都可以找到它们的踪迹
They occupied almost every corner of the globe
而它们的体型和大小各异
and came in almost every shape and size imaginable.
有些恐龙确实非常独特
Some were truly extraordinary.
如今 我们知道霸王龙是游泳健将
We now know that T. rex was a powerful swimmer,
迅猛龙则是长着羽毛的狡猾猎手
Velociraptors were cunning, feathered hunters,
有些恐龙的行为相当怪异
and that some dinosaurs had the most bizarre behavior.
然而 几乎每天都有新的发现
But new discoveries are being made almost every day
揭示更多关于六千六百万年前 地球上生物的故事
that tell us more about life on this planet 66 million years ago.
本季的《Prehistoric Planet》中
This time on Prehistoric Planet,
我们将展示全新的动物
we reveal new animals...
和关于它们寻找伴侣的新发现
and new insight into their quest to find a partner,
抚养一个家庭所面临的挑战
the challenges faced by raising a family...
以及它们间重量级的战斗
and their titanic battles.
带领您穿越时光 探访大自然最壮丽的那个时代
Journey to a time when nature put on its greatest show.
尽在《Prehistoric Planet 2》
This is Prehistoric Planet 2.
荒地
第二季第二集
本WEB版外挂字幕由  风吹来的那片云  双语合并
这是一亿年来 地球上最大的一片熔岩流所覆盖的区域
This is the largest expanse of lava to flood the earth for 100 million years.
印度中部的德干
The Deccan in central India,
一个如同地狱般的地方
a hellish place
当然 这里并非你能想到的恐龙出没之地
and certainly not where you would expect to find dinosaurs.
然而 巨大的恐龙 却冒着生命危险来到了这里
And yet, giants risk their lives traveling here.
伊希斯龙
Isisaurs.
而且它们都是雌性
And all are females.
在德干 熔岩源源不断地涌动
Lava has been flowing in the Deccan for so long
久而久之 有些地方 岩浆的厚度达到了1.6公里
that in places, it is a mile thick.
每年春天 雌性伊希斯龙 都会离开安全的森林家园
Every spring, females leave the safety of their forest home
踏上危险的旅程 进入这片荒地
to make a perilous journey into these badlands.
尽管它们可以在冷却硬化的熔岩上 选择一条安全路线
They can pick a safe route through cooled, hardened lava...
但这里还充斥着其他危险
but there are other dangers here.
除了蒸汽外 火山喷口 还会喷出致命的二氧化碳和
In addition to the steam, a deadly mixture of carbon dioxide and hydrogen sulfide
硫化氢混合物
spews from volcanic vents.
在黎明前的凉爽空气中
In the cool pre-dawn air,
这些沉重的气体会下沉
these heavy gases sink
形成一层几乎看不见的 令人窒息的毒气帷幕
to create a barely visible, suffocating blanket.
仅仅吸入几口就足以致命
Just a few lungfuls can kill.
然而 伊希斯龙异龙有一个关键的优势
But isisaurs have one crucial advantage.
它们的长脖子可以让头部 保持在这片有毒气体之上
Their long necks can keep their heads above this blanket of poisonous fumes.
但在前方的某处 它们很难使头部远离有毒气体
But ahead lies a place where this will be hard to do.
它们正进入一个低洼地带
They're entering a low-lying area
那里的致命气体特别浓厚
where the deadly gases are particularly thick.
而这些雌性伊希斯龙 已经感觉有些不对劲了
And for these females, something is already wrong.
更糟糕的是 当太阳升起 温暖了空气后
And worse, as the sun rises and warms the air,
有毒气体会上升得更高
the gases swirl even higher.
长脖子已经不能保护这群恐龙了
Long necks can no longer protect the herd.
它们必须迅速逃到更高的地方
They must escape to higher ground and quickly.
虽然高地很陡峭 但在上面应该有更新鲜的空气
The climb is steep but should bring fresher air.
它们终于得救了
Relief at last.
前方是它们此次旅程的最终目的地
And ahead, their final destination.
一个高耸入云的火山岛
A volcanic island in the sky
屹立于这片险恶的荒地之上
rising high above these treacherous badlands.
这个巨大的火山口是一个破火山口 为它们提供了一个安全的集体筑巢地
The huge crater, a caldera, provides a safe communal nesting ground.
周围环绕的层层有毒气体 有助于阻挡捕食者进入
The surrounding sea of poisonous gases helps to keep predators away...
同时 内置的地热加热系统 使这里成为理想的孵化器
and the inbuilt geothermal heating makes it an ideal incubator.
每个恐龙妈妈都在温暖的沙地上 挖一个2米深的沟
Each mother digs a seven-foot trench in the warm sand
用来放置超过20个像瓜那么大的蛋
to hold over 20 melon-sized eggs.
这些蛋在这个破火山口暂时很安全
The eggs are safe in the caldera for now,
但这仅仅是它们故事的开始
but this is just the beginning of their story.
在几个月后
In a few months,
成百上千的恐龙宝宝将孵化出来 面对这个荒凉的世界
hundreds of tiny babies will hatch to face this desolate world.
如果想要活下来
If any are to survive,
它们需要周围条件恰到好处的变化
they'll need a perfectly timed change in conditions.
在史前地球上的荒地
The badlands of the prehistoric planet
就连恐龙都受到了生与死的考验
tests even dinosaurs to their limits.
这片奇特的景观
This strange landscape
由侵蚀性的强风和巨大的古河流塑造而成
carved by scouring winds and vast ancient rivers
看似寸草不生
might appear empty of life.
然而在亚洲
But here in Asia,
这些峡谷的蜿蜒深处
hidden in these narrow canyons...
隐藏着一个新生的迅猛龙家族
is a new family of Velociraptors.
这些幼崽才几周大
The young are just a few weeks old.
在这贫瘠的环境中 它们似乎面临着未知的命运
It might seem that in such a barren place, they face an uncertain future.
它们的生存取决于一个奇怪事件 发生在离它们家数公里外的地方
Their survival relies on a strange event, not here, but miles from their home.
在炙热的沙漠对面 有一片被沙海环抱的森林
Across the baking desert lies a forest trapped in a sea of sand.
季节的变化为这片区域带来了稀有的水源
A change in the seasons brings rare water to this region.
大片的白杨树
Huge stands of poplar trees
冒出营养丰富的叶子 标志着雨水的到来
mark its arrival with a flush of nutritious leaves.
这会引来大量饥肠辘辘的动物
A magnet that draws many hungry animals.
长颈的耐梅盖特龙 与蒙古泰坦巨龙一起前来
Long necked nemegtosaurs are joined by Mongolian titanosaurs...
同行的还有体型小得多的倾头龙
and with them, much smaller Prenocephale.
但在它们的旅程中
But one thing stands in their way.
一片广袤的高原阻挡了去路
This immense plateau.
唯一抵达森林的途径 就是穿越这迷宫般的峡谷
And the only way to reach the forest is through this maze of canyons.
当这群恐龙进入峡谷时 它们变得紧张起来
As they enter, the herd becomes nervous.
这里是伏击的好地方
It's a good place for an ambush.
迅猛龙正恭候在此
The Velociraptors are waiting.
但它们无法战胜泰坦巨龙
But they can't possibly tackle a titanosaur.
伏击能否成功取决于其他潜行的猎手
Success will depend instead on other hunters on the prowl.
特暴龙
Tarbosaurs.
亚洲版的霸王龙
Asia's version of Tyrannosaurus rex.
随着掠食者的逼近 恐慌蔓延开来
As the predators approach, panic spreads.
只有倾头龙能逃到更高的地方
Only the Prenocephale can escape to higher ground.
迅猛龙等待的正是这个时刻
And this is what the Velociraptors have waited for.
现在 它们终于可以发动致命的伏击
Now, the Velociraptors can finally spring their ambush.
终于得手
At last.
它们齐心协力为整个家族 争取到了一顿美餐
Working together, they have secured a meal for the whole family.
特暴龙也成功捕获了猎物
The tarbosaurs have also had success.
对于掠食者来说 这实际上是一个食物充足的时期
For predators, it's actually a time of plenty.
对于迅猛龙来说 现在是组建家庭的最佳时机
And for the Velociraptors, the perfect time to start a family.
有智慧且充满关爱的父母 能为孩子提供一个美好的开始
Having clever, caring parents can give youngsters an excellent start.
在亚洲的荒地上
And here in the badlands of Asia,
还有一群更敬业的恐龙父母
there are few more dedicated dinosaur parents than these.
它们就是正在筑巢的冠盗龙
A colony of nesting Corythoraptors.
几天前 雌性冠盗龙 在这些圆形土丘上产下了蛋
A few days ago, females laid eggs on these circular mounds.
而孵蛋的重担则落在了雄性身上
But the job of brooding them falls to the males.
而这并不容易
And that is not easy.
暴露在正午的阳光下 这些蛋很快就会被烤熟
Exposed to the midday sun, the eggs would soon cook.
但是爸爸们用它们 宽大的尾巴和前臂上的羽毛
But the fathers use their broad tail and forearm feathers
为鸟巢遮荫
to keep the nest shaded.
并付出沉重的代价
And pay a heavy price.
承受着长时间的高温
Enduring hour after hour in the searing heat.
终于 在凉爽的夜晚 雄性冠盗龙可以离开去寻找食物
At last, in the cool of the evening, the males can step away in search of food.
这正是群体孵化带来的好处
This is when nesting in a colony brings benefits.
冠盗龙爸爸们并没有同时离开 而是轮流去觅食
Instead of all leaving at once, the Corythoraptors take turns.
因此 总有一个邻居在站岗 密切注意着可能的危险
So, there's always a neighbor keeping an eye out for danger.
然而 即使是邻里守望 也不能保证它们的安全
But even this neighborhood watch can't guarantee their safety.
一只雌性作明龙 迅猛龙的近亲
A female Kuru kulla, a relative of Velociraptors.
它饥肠辘辘 但提防着
She is extremely hungry but wary
冠盗龙有力的喙和爪子
of the Corythoraptors' powerful beaks and claws.
不过 它拥有一个关键优势
But she has one key advantage.
它的夜视能力远胜于巢穴的主人们
Her night vision is better than that of the owners of the nests.
如果它悄无声息 就可以不被察觉地潜入冠盗龙群
If she's quiet, she can sneak into the colony undetected.
它谨慎地选定目标
She picks her target carefully.
机会来了
This is her chance.
但它不是去攻击
But not to attack.
这个掠食者也是个小偷
This predator is also a thief.
它会以最快的速度吃掉尽可能多的蛋
She will eat as many eggs as fast as she can.
时间到了 它被发现了
Time's up. She's been discovered.
带上最后一个蛋逃之夭夭
One last egg to take away.
现在 这个小偷有机会 安静地享用偷来的蛋了
She now has a chance to enjoy her stolen egg in peace.
但它并未独自享用战利品
But this thief shares her spoils.
它用呼噜声召唤自己的孩子们
With these purring sounds, she calls her young.
这些幼崽刚刚离巢不久
Her chicks are not long out of the nest themselves.
它们需要知道这个陌生的新物体是食物
They need to learn that this strange new object is food.
然后发现如何打破它
And discover how to break into it.
或许是用喙 或许是用爪子
Maybe their beak or perhaps a claw.
成功了 虽然这次胜利 更多地依赖运气而非技巧
Success, perhaps more by luck than skill.
但对于下一代偷蛋贼来说 这仍然是一堂重要的生存课程
But still a vital lesson for this next generation of egg thieves.
在荒地上 凉爽的夜晚很短暂
In the badlands, the relief of cooler nights
紧接着是炽热的阳光倾泻
is all too soon followed by the return of the intense heat of the sun's rays.
沙子表面的温度能迅速升至摄氏70度以上
The temperature on the surface of the sand can soar to over 160 degrees Fahrenheit.
这里的水分几乎会在瞬间渗透或蒸发
Any water here soaks away or evaporates in seconds.
这是地球上最干旱的地方之一
This is one of the driest places on earth.
没有水 任何动物都无法生存
Without water, no animal can survive.
然而 这是这些小多智龙的家园
Yet this is home to these young Tarchia.
它们是生活在沙漠中的甲龙
They are desert-living ankylosaurs.
拥有厚实的甲片和巨大的棒状尾巴
Heavily armored with huge, clubbed tails.
深色“眼罩”保护着多智龙的眼睛 免受刺眼阳光的侵害
Dark patches protect the Tarchia's eyes from the glaring sun.
这就是多智龙独特的
And this is the sound
空调系统的声音
of Tarchia's very own air conditioning system.
当空气从身体内排出时 它们的大鼻子能有效地冷却空气
Their large nose cools the air as it leaves the body,
每次呼吸都能凝结并保存宝贵的水分
condensing and so conserving valuable water with every breath.
这使得它们在寻找食物的过程中
It allows them to survive long periods without drinking
可以长时间不喝水
as they search for a meal.
这里的高温形成了侵蚀风
The high temperatures here create scouring winds
将岩石切割成奇异的形状
which carve the rocks into extraordinary shapes.
但它们也会吹走地面土壤
But they also strip the ground of soil.
尽管如此 一些植物 依然在岩石缝隙间扎根
Some plants, however, manage to take root in cracks between the rocks.
哪怕只能吃上一小口 也值得为之竞争
Any meager mouthful is worth competing for.
每过一分钟 太阳就升得更高
With every minute, the sun climbs higher.
阴凉处会消失殆尽
Soon, all shade will be gone.
即使作为沙漠之主的多智龙 有时也渴望能喝上一口水
And even these masters of the desert welcome a drink sometimes.
像许多游牧民族一样
Like many nomads,
多智龙的脑海中有一幅沙漠地图
the Tarchia have a mental map of the desert
能够准确地穿越空旷的地形
and can travel across empty landscapes with unerring accuracy.
它们记住了那些天然泉水所在的稀有地点
They remember the rare places where there are natural springs.
像这样的沙漠绿洲
Desert oases like this one.
对能找到它们的动物来说简直是救命稻草
A lifesaver for animals that can find them.
倾头龙
Prenocephale.
绿洲周围的气氛常常异常紧张
Tensions often run high around an oasis...
然而 展示力量可以避免一场危险的战斗
but a display of strength can prevent a dangerous battle.
倾头龙终究不过是一种骚扰
In the end, the Prenocephale are little more than annoying.
但成年多智龙就是另一回事了
But an adult Tarchia is another matter.
尤其是体重几乎是 年幼多智龙两倍的成年龙
Especially one almost twice the youngster's weight.
它挥舞着重达22公斤的棒状尾巴
It wields a club weighing almost 50 pounds.
如果打起来 年幼的多智龙无法取胜
If this comes to a fight, the juvenile can't win.
但援军正在赶来
But reinforcements are on the way.
这一对多智龙重聚
The pair are reunited.
现在成年龙要对付之前两倍的棒状尾巴
Now there are twice as many swinging clubs for the adult to deal with.
它决定也许这里有足够的水
He decides that perhaps there is enough water here
供大家共享
for everyone to share.
年幼的多智龙终于得以安心地饮水
The young Tarchia can finally drink in peace.
然而 它们可能无法长时间休憩
But they may not be able to enjoy their rest for long.
荒地上天气变化的速度十分惊人
In badlands, conditions can change with astonishing speed.
夏季气温的上升引发了宽达数百公里的
Rising summer temperatures fuel electric storms
闪电风暴
hundreds of miles wide.
在德干 这些季节性风暴 导致风向发生改变
Here in the Deccan, these seasonal storms cause a shift in the wind direction.
几个月前 雌性伊希斯龙
And around the caldera
在这些破火山口附近产蛋
where the isisaur females laid their eggs months ago,
如今有毒气体已被风吹散
the poisonous gases have now blown away,
为幼龙宝宝提供了一个 关键的生存机会窗口
providing a critical window of opportunity.
沙子下 奇特的声音响起
There are strange sounds coming from beneath the sand.
小伊希斯龙在蛋里呼唤着彼此
Baby isisaurs are calling to each other from inside their eggs.
这有助于它们同步孵化
It helps to synchronize their hatching.
这些幼龙相对较小 身长不到30厘米
The babies are relatively tiny, less than a foot long.
这里除了妈妈的粪便 没什么可吃的
There's nothing to eat except their mothers' dung.
意想不到的是
Surprisingly,
粪便富含营养 在很多其他方面 也对幼龙宝宝至关重要
it's very nutritious and important to the hatchlings in other ways too.
它将有益的细菌带入它们的肠道
It introduces healthy bacteria into their guts,
同时还含有信息素 就像气味一样
and it also contains pheromones that, like smells,
能引导它们找到母亲所在的群体
will enable them to find their mothers' herd.
带领它们前往森林的安全之地
It will lead them to the safety of the forest.
然而 这段旅程并非易事
But the journey isn't easy.
尽管风向的改变对它们有利
The winds may have changed in their favor,
这些年幼的伊希斯龙仍面临诸多危险
but many dangers lie ahead for the young isisaurs.
温泉和冒泡的液体泥浆池
Hot springs and bubbling pools of liquid mud.
是致命的陷阱
A deadly trap.
历经两天的跋涉
After two days of trekking,
幼龙宝宝们的能量储备几近耗尽
the babies' reserves are running low...
然而母亲们再次拯救了它们
but their mothers have come to the rescue again.
小植物已在破裂的熔岩中生根
Small plants have taken root in the cracked lava,
由掉落在恐龙母亲粪便中的种子发芽
sprouting from seeds dropped in the mothers' dung.
然而新的危险正在逼近
But a new danger is heading their way.
如今有毒气体消散 掠食者也随之而来
Now the wind has cleared the toxic gases, the door opens for predators.
一只胜王龙现身
A rajasaur.
有这么多恐龙宝宝暴露在外 这也许是一场盛宴
With so many babies out in the open, this could be a feast.
熔岩裂缝成了唯一的藏身之地
Cracks in the lava are the only possible hiding place.
来了更多的胜王龙
More rajasaurs arrive.
尽管危险重重 成百上千的幼龙宝宝 终于成功抵达了森林
Despite the dangers, hundreds of babies succeed in reaching the forest.
在这里 它们将一同 躲藏在灌木丛中生活数年
Here, they will live together hidden in the undergrowth for several years.
直至最终长得足够大
Until finally
有能力加入母亲们的群体
they are big enough to join their mothers' herds.
如果幸运的话 它们中的雌性将在未来几年
With luck, the females among them will return to this crater
回到这个火山口产下自己的蛋
in years to come to lay eggs of their own.
正如许多生活在 这些恶劣环境中的动物一样
Like many animals that live in such inhospitable places,
风险巨大
the risks will be high.
然而 在史前地球的荒地上 同样蕴藏着无数机遇
But there are also great opportunities in the badlands of the prehistoric planet.
(揭秘《Prehistoric Planet》)
(恐龙是好父母吗 )
这是一个巨型恐龙的蛋化石
This is the fossilized egg of a giant dinosaur.
来自泰坦巨龙
A titanosaur.
蛋刚产出时
When freshly laid,
重约1.5公斤
it would have weighed around a kilo and a half,
外壳厚约2毫米
and its shell is about two millimeters thick.
尽管蛋很坚硬
While the eggs certainly were tough,
它们仍需要保持安全和温暖
they still needed to be kept safe and warm.
那么 恐龙是如何照顾它们的蛋呢
So how did dinosaurs take care of their eggs?
为了保护自己的蛋免受掠食者的侵害
In order to protect their eggs from predators
并保持蛋的温度 恐龙演化出一系列策略
and to keep their eggs warm, dinosaurs evolved a list of strategies.
(首席科学顾问 达伦奈什博士)
其中一个策略是筑巢
One of these strategies was to build a nest
并坐在上面
and then to actually sit on top of the nest.
我们确信某些恐龙会这么做
We know for certain dinosaurs did this
因为我们实际上有恐龙坐在巢顶的化石
because we actually have fossils of dinosaurs sat on top of nests.
在这些巢中发现的蛋里 有与成年恐龙相同种类的
Eggs found in these nests contain tiny babies of the same species
幼崽宝宝
as the adults,
这是有些恐龙
providing the first evidence
会照顾幼崽的第一个证据
that some dinosaurs looked after their young.
尽管这样可以保护蛋不受天气侵害
But although this offered protection and shelter from the elements,
但这种孵化方法也有局限
there was a downside to incubating eggs in this way.
坐在蛋上并真正照看它
Having to sit on an egg and actually look after it means
意味着要在蛋的整个发育过程中
that you are committed to the care of that egg
坚持对其进行照顾
for the entire duration of their development
直到其孵化
up until the point of hatching.
对某些恐龙而言 这是值得的
For some dinosaurs, it was a commitment worth making.
但其他恐龙 如蜥脚龙 面临着不同的挑战
But others, like sauropods, faced a different challenge.
由于许多恐龙体重达数吨
It's likely that some dinosaurs never sat on their eggs.
它们可能从未坐在蛋上
After all, many of these animals weighed tons and tons
(自然历史博物馆 保罗巴雷特教授)
以免在孵化前将蛋压碎
and would have crushed them before they had any chance of hatching.
那么它们又有何解决方案呢
So, what was their solution?
一些蜥脚龙的蛋被放置在
There are some sauropod egg clutches
雌性用后脚挖出的长沟中
where the female excavated a long trench with her back feet.
产完蛋后 雌性会再将沟填满
She then backfilled the trench once she had laid all the eggs.
如今仍能看到这种行为
This behavior can be seen today.
海龟把蛋埋起来 从而保护它们不受掠食者的侵害
Turtles bury their eggs to protect them from predators,
阳光温暖的沙子使蛋保持理想温度
and the sun-warmed sand keeps them at the ideal temperature.
然而 有些恐龙采用另一种方法保持蛋温
But some dinosaurs had another trick to keep their eggs warm.
我们认为 某些恐龙群体会故意收集腐烂植被
We think some dinosaur groups deliberately collected
堆积在巢顶
and piled up rotting vegetation.
基本上在装满蛋的巢上形成了一个肥堆
They basically formed a compost heap on top of their egg-filled nests.
澳大利亚的丛林火鸡 使用这种了不起的技巧
Bush turkeys in Australia use this remarkable technique.
植被分解释放出的热量
As the vegetation breaks down,
足以让蛋孵化
it releases enough heat to incubate their eggs
七周左右
for around seven weeks.
然而 2010年的一项发现
But it was a discovery in 2010
揭示了某些恐龙采用了更不同寻常的方式
that revealed that some dinosaurs had an even more unusual way
来保持它们的蛋温暖
of keeping their eggs warm.
它们利用地球本身的热量
They use heat from the earth itself.
在阿根廷的一个特定地点
In one particular site in Argentina
发现了大量蜥脚龙蛋
that's had lots of sauropod egg discoveries,
就靠近一些地热温泉
it's right next door to some geothermal springs.
我们认为蜥脚龙利用火山活动
We're thinking the sauropods were using that volcanic activity
来帮助蛋保暖
to help keep its eggs warm.
德干地区是另一个相关地点
Another location, the Deccan region of India,
这里是白垩纪晚期 火山活动最为频繁的地区之一
one of the most volcanic areas during the late Cretaceous,
这个地区提供了更多证据
provides more evidence.
那里有很多层熔岩
There are many, many layers of lava,
在熔岩流之间 我们发现了恐龙蛋
then in between the lava flows, we find dinosaur eggs.
恐龙选择在这里筑巢
Dinosaurs were coming to this location
即使是在火山高度活跃的时候
even when it was highly active volcanically,
这个地方也作为筑巢地被使用了数个世纪
using it as a nesting site for literally centuries.
总之 恐龙采用了多种方法 确保它们的蛋能成功孵化
Dinosaurs had many ways to ensure their eggs would hatch...
然而 我们可以确定的是
but we can be certain of one thing.
它们的方法非常有效
Their methods worked very effectively,
使恐龙能够统治地球超过一亿五千万年
helping them to rule the world for over 150 million years.
字幕翻译:谭萱